<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research on Noboru Murata</title>
    <link>https://noboru-murata.github.io/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research on Noboru Murata</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0900</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://noboru-murata.github.io/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Information Geometry</title>
      <link>https://noboru-murata.github.io/research/information-geometry/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://noboru-murata.github.io/research/information-geometry/</guid>
      <description>Information geometry is a relatively new field of mathematical science that discusses geometry in the space of probability distributions, and uses a characteristic structure called the dual connection. By reconsidering the relationship between examples (data) collected from a certain probability distribution and a learning machine that models data structur in the space of probability distributions, we can discuss the properties of machine learning algorithms.
Boosting by Well-Designed Ensemble Boosting is an algorithm specific to machine learning that efficiently collects weak learners and augments them into a strong learner.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biological Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://noboru-murata.github.io/research/biological-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://noboru-murata.github.io/research/biological-data/</guid>
      <description>Biological system can be regarded as a high-dimensional dynamical system with a complex structure. There are only a few variables that can be observed externally in an uncertain and noisy environment. In many cases, there is a large discrepancy between what we want to know and what we can measure.
The key issues are how to model the generation mechanism of observable data in a way that concisely models the essential parts of the structure we want to know, and how to efficiently and accurately estimate unknown parameters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://noboru-murata.github.io/research/machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://noboru-murata.github.io/research/machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>In statistical machine learning, we consider the problem of inferring the probability structure behind data from a relatively small number of examples. The key is how to model the probability structure that generates the data and how to efficiently solve the unknown parameters.
We consider the properties of various learning machines, the dynamics of optimization, and the statistical properties of the estimated parameters from the standpoint of mathematical science.
Universality of Multi-Layer Perceptron It has been proved from various points of view that the neural network is a universal function approximator that can approximate arbitrary nonlinear functions sufficiently well.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
